[Music]
Stanford
University let's
start with some
philosophy let's start with some general
philosophical
principle it's a principle that
philosophers call
reductionism
reductionism is the principle or the
philosophy
that big things are made out of little
things and little things are made out of
little
things that's one element of
reductionism how many people would agree
with reductionism
here yeah I mean you
know uh molecules are made out of atoms
atoms are made out of electrons and
nuclei nuclei are made out of protons
and neutrons protons and neutrons are
made out of quarks and gluons and so
forth
uh I call that uh the building block
theory that houses are made out of
bricks bricks are made out of molecules
and nobody in their right mind mistakes
a house for a brick right we all know
the bricks from the houses the bricks
are smaller than the houses they're also
simpler than the houses so that's
another element of reductionism as you
go deeper and deeper into the layer of
reductionism things get simpler or at
least we hope they do that's that's a
Pious hope of
reductionism I
think from what we've learned both from
String Theory from the quantum mechanics
of gravity and so forth that modern
theories really do spell the end of
reductionism but before you in
reductionism it's interesting to ask how
well it does as a philosophy and as a uh
as a theory of Elementary
particles
if reductionism is Right particularly in
that aspect which has to do with
Simplicity as you go deeper and deeper
you might have expected that by now
elementary particle physics would be
pretty
simple we've gone several several layers
and is it simple the answer is no it is
very very complicated and to measure how
complicated it is you can simply ask how
many different kinds of
particles are there and in particular
particles which are
unexplained well there's something like
about 75 different
particles all of which in a standard
model of particle physics and the
standard model of particle physics maybe
only about about 20 or maybe even a
little bit less than that independent
particles that don't have tight
relationships between each other so it's
maybe 10 to 15 or 20 uh distinct
different particles depending on how you
count how many parameters parameters
again mean unexplained constants that
have to go into the theory to make sense
out of it well about
20 20 distinct
parameters but the theory is definitely
incomplete we know that it's incomplete
it doesn't have gravity it doesn't have
dark matter it doesn't have the
particles that are necessary for
inflation uh the theory of uh Cosmic
inflation to make
sense and it has a terrible fine-tuning
problem we've talked about that
fine-tuning problem
that in order to overcome this
people introduce things like super
symmetry my guess is that super symmetry
will really be discovered at the LHC but
if it does it adds about a 100 new
parameters well I take that back it's
100 plus n where n is an unknown
number
but that n is not zero because it's
necessary for understanding the breaking
of super symmetry why super symmetry is
not a real uh another 100 parameters a
doubling of the number of all of the
particles plus a whole bunch of stuff
that's necessary for inflation and other
things by the time you finish the
standard model of particle physics
together with all of the bells and
whistles that have to be added to
understand everything let's say is a
theory with about 200 parameters huge
number of
particles uh and totally unexplained
connections so it's not simple it's it's
very very
complicated and
complicated either you have to say well
we haven't gotten anywhere as near the
bottom yet or we just have to admit that
maybe reductionism isn't
working but the fact the idea that
reductionism isn't
working that's not what I meant when I
said
modern theories sort of spell the end of
reductionism what I meant was a more
theoretical
fact uh a more theoretical fact based on
both Quantum field Theory and string
theory so I'll tell you a little bit
about what is
known in particular about the idea that
endlessly well not necessarily endlessly
but that uh that Des that we can always
tell the bricks from the
houses is it really always true that we
can tell which thing is more fundamental
than which thing I'm going to give you
some a couple of examples of places
where in Quantum field theory that idea
has broken down broken down badly the
first example was an example of a very
simple kind I'm not going to explain
this I'm just going to tell you about
it it was studying the quantum field
theory of onedimensional systems
models models in which there was time
and only one dimension of space very
easy to draw a dimension of space and a
dimension of
time and that's all there is and
particles what was discovered is that
there's a simple there number just in
fact almost every theory in uh of this
type can be described in terms of
particles which are Fons remember what
Fons are Fons are particles
that satisfy the PO Exclusion Principle
they're the particles which have this
odd behavior that they can't go into the
state you can't put two of them into the
same
state electrons are fion quarks are
fion uh photons are not firion they're
bosons the opposite of a firon is a
boson and all particles are either
firion or bosons so in this mathematical
Theory uh
you start with some particles which are
firion the firon field the object which
describes the Fons which creates and
annihilates the Fons we called
Sai right let's the mathematical
terminology is not important here what
is important is that the basic starting
point is a field theory of
Fons now what happens if you put two
Fons
together what do you make
if if you put two of them identical ones
together you make zero but supposing two
not quite identical ones one sort of
right next to the other but not right on
top of it then you make a
bon okay for example protons are Fons
electrons are fermion hydrogen atoms are
bosons okay so you take a firon and a b
two fion and you put them together
almost together maybe uh there's some
attractive force between them which
holds them together and these
particles which are now Composites
they're clearly Composites they can move
up and down they're also particles but
they're composite
particles those composite particles are
bosons and bons are also described by
Fields you would think that it's not
really a fundamental field you would
think that it's a field
that is some effective
description of the two particles stuck
together and you call it Fi Fi creates
bosons it creates pairs of these
Fons that sounds very in very uh very
straightforward but what was then
discovered in these field theories is
that you could rewrite exactly the same
field theory in terms of an underlying
starting point which started with the
bans let's draw that field Theory over
here now you start with the bosons the
firion cannot be composits of the bosons
because any number of bosons put
together make another
boson but these Fons can be described in
a totally new way they're described if
we plot this is not plotting time
anymore this is plotting the field
fi as what's called a kink in the field
f a place where the field F jumps
smoothly jumps doesn't doesn't jump ra
suddenly it smoothly jumps over a
distance some distance jumps from one
value to another it's called a
kink it's called a kink if you want to
picture it I should have taken off my
belt while I uh I won't take off my belt
but imagine my belt
here it is and here I've laid it out on
the Blackboard so that it's not
Twisted that's got no Kink now take the
belt and twist it rotate this end around
by two Pi so it's twisted once it comes
back to its original configuration over
here its original configuration over
here but in between
it's twisted that's a
kink that's a kink in my belt right I
often do that I I often do that when I
put my belt on and then discover uh uh
two hours later when I'm talking to
somebody that my belt is on wrong right
that's called a
kink the bizarre thing is that these
Fons that we start we thought we started
with the bricks which built the houses
the Fon bricks which build the ban
houses can now be re-presented as kinks
in the ban
field Kinks which are
extended
thick and
massive much heavier than the
bans which are the houses which are the
bricks nobody can say it's entirely
equivalent there are parameters in such
a theory field theories have
parameters it turns out that for some
values of the some ranges of the
parameters it's much more convenient to
think of the firion as the fundamental
building
blocks and for another range of the
parameters the Bans are much more
efficient at studying the theory and
they are the more useful building blocks
it simply becomes a matter of which is
more useful is it more useful to think
of Sai the firion or five bosons as the
fundamental objects of the
theory and that depends on the
parameters that depends on a coupling
constant a coupling constant that's
usually called G it doesn't matter what
it's called so starting with very small
G you discover that it's much more
useful to think of the firion as the
starting point easy to deal with easy to
study these things are composits that
are held together by complicated
forces now you start changing this
coupling con and increasing it and
increasing oh incidentally when that g
is very
small uh let's see that Kink
is um very tight very small like
that now you start changing the cou and
that's why the firon is a small object
the firon is a small object because it's
a small Kink now you start tuning the
coupling constant making it stronger and
stronger what happens is the king starts
to spread
out it gets less and less pointlike
but the Bon starts to behave more and
more like a simple Elementary object so
the question of which is fundamental and
which is composite doesn't have a unique
answer by varying the constants you can
make you can morph you can make a one
thing go into the other the houses go
into the bricks so to speak
um that was a case that was known oh
geez since I was a very young
physicist
um the key word is called bosonization
it's making a firmon out of bosons or
for bosons out of Fons all right are
there any things like this in elementary
particle physics It is believed that
there
are and the belief centers around
electric and magnetic monopoles let me
tell you what an electric and magnetic
monopole is an electric
monopole could be an electron could be
any charged
particle ordinary charged particle
surrounded by an electric field usual
electric
field and let's take these uh let's take
the particle to be let's say an
electron the electric charge of an
electron is very weak as a matter of
fact
it's a very weak electric charge the
amount of charge and not just because
the electron is
small that's actually not the uh the
issue there's a dimensionless quantity
what's the dimensionless quantity called
anybody
know the fine structure
constant the F yeah the fine structure
constant is a measure of how much an
electron would radiate if you you know
if you accelerated it suddenly or if you
plowed it into a uh
an anode if you plowed it into a stop
into a uh you know how much would it
radiate how many photons would it
radiate the answer is that an electron
will radiate on the average about 1 over
100 photons another way of saying it is
the electron will only radiate about one
out of a 100 times when it's stopped
radiate a photon so the electron charge
is very
weak um
the electron is very simple the electric
field around it is rather is uh is
rather weak because the electric charge
is weak and it doesn't do very much to
the neighboring space around it it
doesn't polarize the vacuum it doesn't
create electron positron pairs to any
appreciable
amount electron is
simple it is also believed that in
nature there do exist magnetic monopoles
most physicists like myself believe
believe in the existence of magnetic
monopoles
they they come up in so many theories
that by
now they but they've never been
discovered they've never been discovered
in the laboratory a magnetic
monopole is like the end of a bar
magnet
north south if you just imagine the end
of the bar magnet with the bar magnet
itself being so thin that you couldn't
see
it then waving around the bar magnet
would look like waving
around a magnetic
monopole where the magnetic field comes
out of the magnetic monopole exactly the
same way the electric field comes out of
the electric
monopole the man the monopoles that
theoretical physics seems to uh
produce have a magnetic charge which is
huge very large the force between two
magnetic monopoles would be 10,000 times
larger than the force between two
electrons at the same distance that
means that the maget magnetic monopoles
make large fields around them and do
very very complicated things make a very
complicated mess around them that
complicated mess is
extended it's broad the same way that
the Kink was Broad and it's massive it's
very very heavy because there's so much
going on in the vicinity of the monopole
I'm not really talking about the end of
a bar
magnet I'm talking about the end of the
bar magnet without the bar magnet
magnetic monopoles they haven't been
discovered in the laboratory because
they're too heavy to
make will they ever be discovered
perhaps but most theorists believe in
them but the point is the more important
point is the mathematics of quantum
electrodynamics
which contains monopoles and electrons
is totally unclear about which of them
is the elementary
particle it depends on the fine
structure constant it depends
on Alpha the fine structure constant if
the fine structure constant which is
basically the square of the electric
charge of the electron if that's much
much less than one then the electron is
the simple one it's simple it's almost
Point like it has very little structure
the charge is very
weak the monopole has a very very
complicated structure in that limit the
magnetic field is very powerful and does
very complicated things to space around
it and that's why it's
heavy what happens if you could imagine
now that you had a dial that you could
start dialing redialing the fine
structure constant start increasing it
what happens as you start to increase it
the field surrounding the electron
becomes
stronger effectively the electric charge
is getting larger the field is getting
stronger it starts to do more
complicated things in the vicinity of
the
electron what happens to the magnetic
monopole the magnetic monopole starts to
shrink this is not something we can that
I can uh explain easily but the fact is
it starts to shrink it gets smaller and
smaller it gets lighter and lighter the
electron gets heavier and heavier as
Alpha gets
large when Alpha gets bigger than
one they simply
interchange the magnetic monopole
becomes light and small and
fundamental the electron would become
heavy complicated and full of all kinds
of structure and basically they would
just in change
themselves so again which is the
building block is it the
electron whose uh complicated structure
here is making up the monopole or is it
the monopole which is simple and whose
complicated structure is making up the
electron modern Quantum field theor say
they're equivalent you can't tell the
difference of
course you may want to choose one of
them as the start starting point
depending on the fine structure constant
it may be more convenient to think of
the electron as fundamental and less
convenient to think about the monopole
and that of course is true and that's
why we use electrons as starting points
for Quantum electrodynamics and not
monopoles
um yeah yeah um getting back to your
philosophical point if if there's a
belief that reductionism is not the
correct view of things why do physicists
use calculus which is the most
reductionist of mathematical
tools um calculus is not necessarily
reductionist it just says everything is
smooth smoothly
varying uh but it doesn't in any way
tell you what the fundamental objects
are Theory but but with uh with like a
derivative you you chop it up into teeny
weeny little point and then
right right right you chopped up things
into little little distances and you ask
what's in those little
distances and that tells you what the
what the fundamental things are
okay in Quantum field
Theory it's just an endless hierarchy of
distance
scales and so you never get to the point
where you can decide which one is
fundamental like a fractal hm like a
fractal like a fractal yeah very much
like aact but for for example describing
a curve you can use it using a
derivative or one of the few
non-reductionist uh models this general
relativity where you describe it as a
geodesic under Quantum Fields fluctuate
and they fluctuate on every
scale so they're never
smooth they're never
smooth and in some sense
some of the the great difficulties of
understanding Quantum field Theory the
reasons that mathem mathematicians have
so much trouble with
it is sort of because in a certain sense
calculus does break
down um in studying the fields they
fluctuate too much they vary too much
but uh let's not get into that now all
right now what do String Theory say does
string theory have an answer to what is
what are the fundamental building blocks
well obviously string theory has an
answer for what the fundamental building
blocks is it must be strings right okay
so let me tell you a little bit about we
talked about de brains
yes all right so I will just very
quickly just remind you what a Deb brain
is we don't need to know a lot about the
mathematics pictures are good enough
de brains are objects that were
discovered through a
fairly
um indirect mathematical root they are
part of a theory you can't get rid of
them they're stuck with it their objects
which are first of all very
heavy they could be they come in
different
dimensionality the simplest one is
called the d0o brain and z Z stands for
the dimension what's the what's the
dimension of a point the dimensionality
of a point first of all what's the
dimensionality of a line one dimension
the dimensionality of a membrane or a
two-dimensional Surface Two what's the
dimensionality of a
point
zero so in that sense
particles Point particles are
called zero dimensional objects
even if they're not absolute points
they're still regarded as uh as zero
Dimension dimensional they are not
extended in higher Dimensions so a
particle is a d0o brain the word brain
incidentally b r a n e brain comes from
membrane a membrane a surface is a two
brain or a two brain two-dimensional
brain what's a
string a one brain
what's a three-dimensional block of uh
of uh solid stuff it's a three brain and
can you picture a forbrain no we don't
have enough directions to to put it into
but if we had more directions we could
make four brains all right so a dzero
brain is a kind of
particle the d stands for the
mathematician durish lay and it's not
important but the property of these de
brains in string theory is that they are
places where strings can
end fundamental strings let's call them
F strings this is an F string F standing
for fundamental the building blocks the
things that gravitons are made out of
you know all the good stuff that we've
talked about up till now the fundamental
strings and dzero brains are just sites
on which a fundamental string can end in
fact any number of fundamental strings
can end on a dzero brain and that means
that dzero brains can have strings
attached to them and they typically
do if you were to probe at the zero
brain by scattering something off it you
would find out that it has a collection
of strings attached to it like that in
fact the harder you probed it the more
string you would find closer and closer
in and you would eventually come to the
conclusion that the D brain is in some
sense made up out of strings but it's
got a lot of strings and it's heavy it's
much much heavier than the ordinary
strings themselves it's a little core
that's very massive and that core is a
place where strings can end the
mathematics that went into this to its
Discovery and so forth is less
interesting than the fact that these
things are necessarily forced to exist
they're massive they're
complicated and uh
they are there they're in the theory now
d That's a d0o brain there are also D1
brains D1
brain is like a string what's I just
want to thicken it out because it's much
heavier than an ordinary string much
more mass per unit
length but it also has the property that
it's a place where ordinary strings
fundamental strings can end and so again
it's kind of a uh an object which is
made up out of these strings a sort of
cable a cable a thick cable a thick
cable much thicker than the ordinary
strings and much heavier heavier in the
sense that per unit length its mass is
much
larger very much in a sense well let's
let's draw two strings next to each
other here's a d string and here's an F
string a DZ a D1 brain can also be
called a d
string here's an F string a fundamental
string it's thin it's narrow it's
light these two objects are related in
very much the same way
that this one and this one are related
in very much the same way as can you
guess what I'm going to say
next monopoles and
electrons the fundamental strings are
like the electrons the building blocks
the starting point for string theory
these objects are big heavy composite
structures which are made out of cables
of lots of string they're heavy and
they're obviously
composite string theory has I said it
has no parameters now we're going to
come back to whether we're going to come
back in a minute to the question of
whether it has parameters or not uh for
practical purposes for the moment it
does have a parameter the param is a
coupling constant let's call it
g g is a coupling constant a parameter
of the theory which basically tells you
the probability that if a string is
wiggling around it might split in
half it's very similar in many ways to
the probability that an electron when
accelerated will emit a
photon string wiggling around if you
grab a piece of it and pull it it might
uh it can break
the probability for that is called the
coupling
constant if the coupling constant is
very
small then the F strings are light
they're thin and they look very
fundamental pointlike well not pointlike
but line
like when G is very small the D string
is very heavy very
complicated and full of f
strings guess what happens as you start
increasing
G as you start increasing G the
fundamental string here tends to break
off little pieces those little pieces
don't disappear and fly off they hang
around and they form a kind of I don't
know what to call it an atmosphere uh
around the fundamental
string and the fundamental string gets
more and more complicated in the same
way that the electron got complicated
when you started to increase the F
structure constant the fundamental
string starts to develop
structures at the same time well at the
same time the D string starts to get
simpler the fundamental string gets
heavier because it gets heavier it gets
harder and harder for the D string to
produce fundamental string and so these
structures get thinned out as they get
thinned out the D string gets thinner
and
thinner eventually at some point point
when G is about one they start to look
exactly like each
other and then if you go to even larger
coupling constant the D string gets very
simple turns into a thin linik object
and the fundamental string just gets as
complicated as the D string was
originally which one describes or which
one of these strings when they form
little Loops create particles create
create gravitons create photons and so
forth well if G is much less than one
then the fundamental
strings when they close back on
themselves form the particles the
ordinary particles of uh of string
theory but as G gets larger and larger
these things get more and more massive
in fact eventually they turn into black
holes
and what's left over is the D strings
which get lighter and lighter and the
graviton is made up out of the D
strings this is called D string
fundamental string Duality it's not the
usual name for it it's usually called s
Duality I do not know what s stands for
I didn't make up the
term uh I don't know why it's called oh
strength Duality strength yeah strength
of the coupling constant so again we
find this
pattern that you can't say once and for
all which thing is more fundamental than
which you just find them morphing into
each other now they morph into each
other as the coupling constant varies
but at least you could say well at least
you can say that if the coupling
constant is small then it's profitable
to think of the of the fundamental
strings as fun as fundamental if the
coupling constant is very large switch
them the problem with that is the
coupling constant is something that can
vary in space it's a
field G in string theory is not a
constant it's a thing which can vary
from place to place it satisfies field
equations just like the gravitational
field and so you can easily have a
situation in the mathematically
idealized String Theory where the
coupling constant goes from very strong
to very weak as you move across the
universe and in one place the D strings
are fundamental in the other place the F
strings are fundamental and in between
nothing is
simple that's the character of string
theory question on a cosmological scale
I mean if if it varied
uh became less massive than F wouldn't
that have effect on Spectra and such and
chemistry absolutely that's how we know
that's one of the ways we know that
string theory the the mathematically
precise version of string theory is not
our
world another question so is there a
duel for like the D2 brain yep yeah
we'll talk
about and there's a du like a
fundamental duel for that yeah
yeah yeah there
is um just
uh trying trying to get it straight in
my mind
the greater likelihood of splitting
makes complexity in the Upstream is that
yeah yeah
yeah let's go back to Quantum Electro
Dynamics for a
minute now my vertical axis is time and
here's an electron World
line it's a point that means it's a very
thin World line not it's not a string
vertical remember vertical for a
physicist always means time horizontal
means space all right so here's a point
electron uh moving through time so to
speak that point
electron
emits and absorbs
photons now when the fine structure
constant is very
small the emission and absorption of
photons is very intermittent meaning to
say
uh that there aren't very many of these
photons being
emitted what about the photons
themselves well a
photon can create and annihilate an
electron positron
pair so that means that the
photons can create electron positron
pairs but now each one of these little
electrons here can also emit
photons there's a sort of unending
hierarchy at smaller and smaller
distance scale of structure within the
electron as long as the coupling
constant is weak this is a relatively
small effect in fact it's a small effect
and the electron in the laboratory looks
pretty darn Point like you have to work
very hard to scatter things off it and
see that the electron has this composite
structure there where do the energy come
from it uh it's um where does the energy
come
from uh the energy the
energy The energy needed for this
process is part of the mass of the
proton or mass of the
electron is part of the mass of the
electron it is the mass of it is the
mass of the electron where did the
energy come from to create the Kum field
around the
electron well the point is you don't
start without the Kum field the coom
field was always
there yes but
uh I I don't I see things much too uh
uh uh uh not accurately enough I see two
electron pair being
produced uh and I don't see the mass of
electron enough to produce an electron
pair
it
help
well yeah obviously you know you skin by
by the skin of your teeth have virtual
no but mass and energy are the same
thing and so when you say the mass of
the electron you're basically including
the energy needed to do this kind all
right but what is that energy that
energy is a kind of potential energy
it's a kind of potential
energy uh that's connected with the
interactions between the electrons and
the
photons the energy of a system in
Quantum electrodynamics is not just the
energy of the electrons plus the energy
of the photons there also an interaction
energy between them and that's the that
that interaction energy is the source of
this but
uh all right but it's it's you know it's
an empirical fact that if you scatter
things off an electron at high enough
energy you will see this structure
around the electron see if scattered
with energy then I can see that the
energy of your experiment will produce
What You observe well okay we can we can
debate whether the energy of the
experiment is producing what you see or
whether it's seeing what you
see
um we can debate that but the fact of
the matter is that when you scatter
things off the electron what happens is
complicated what happens is comp well
it's not so complicated most of the
times you don't see anything about 1% of
the time you
seeu on the on De brains uh you said
that uh for a couple of constants small
you say that the uh mass of the of the
D1 brain is more than the mass of the F
string yeah yeah um is and would the
tension also be more do you yeah yeah
the tension the mass means the T the
tension means the mass per unit
length
yeah yeah so mass per unit length is
called the tension right exactly energy
per unit length all right
now
um as I said as the as the fine
structure constant starts to get bigger
and bigger this structure starts to
proliferate and the result is that the
electron develops this very complicated
structure it's no longer something which
is very very rare or very dilute the
electron gets big gets heavy gets all
the structure there very very similar
thing happens to a
string what uh what is this coupling
constant G this coupling constant is the
propability that if the
string fluctuates if it undergoes a
Quantum
fluctuation let's say to a configuration
like that then it's basically the
probability that the string splits
off and forms a little sort of satellite
string around the original
string as the coupling constant gets
larger and larger a very similar thing
happens the satellite strings start to
proliferate and they form a structure
surrounding the string the same way that
the electron positron Pairs and the
photon surrounded the electron they make
it heavier they give it a structure
uh and uh the result is that the F
string starts to look more and more like
the D string in the meantime the D
string has more and more trouble
emitting
or producing F strings why because those
F strings are getting heavier and
heavier and the result is that the D
string gets less and less
structure and becomes more like the F
string so that's that's another example
of a duality these things are called
dualities uh this one's called s Duality
the name is not
important um and it interchanges
fundamental strings with d
strings the mathematics of this by now
is very
tight even though uh I'm not trying at
all to give you the mathematics
now um
there are different versions of string
theory the mathematics of them is not so
important but there are different
versions in one
version all of the de brains are odd
dimensional so that means that there
are D1 brains D3 brains D brains how do
you stick a D5 brain into space we don't
have enough dimensions of space
well remember that string theory is
fundamentally a 10-dimensional theory
you've got a lot of extra
Dimensions string theory has enough
Dimensions that you can put in things up
to about eight
brains uh and then you run out of
directions to put the brains in
so one version of string
theory the mathematics tells you that
there must be D1 D3 D5 D7 brain
brains in another version of string
theory which is closely related but
different there are even dimensional
brains no string theory has both
odd-dimensional Deb brains and even
dimensional it's just a fact that that
the that no version of it has both not
this is by no means transparent I'm
telling you facts more than I'm telling
you
explanations
uh it would take many hours of
mathematics to explain why that's true
but nevertheless this is a fact so let's
go to the version of string theory which
has even dimensional brains instead of
odd dimensional it doesn't have D
strings it has dzero brains it has
pointlike
particles which are not quite pointlike
but which are very complicated and full
of
string and it also has fundamental
strings that make gravitons and so forth
that's the description when the coupling
constant
G is much much less than
one this Theory does something very
different as G starts to get large it
was a great puzzle that nobody knew the
answer to what happens to these objects
as G starts to get large this can't
become this this is a pointlike thing
this is a a string which could be spread
out all over the place there're
different kinds of creatures it's not
the case that one will go back and forth
into the other that's not the way it
works something much more bizarre
happens so I will tell
you let's see before I tell you I have
to
um all right I'm going to tell you what
happened
and perhaps
uh in the second hour I can tell you why
or what what it means for it to happen
what
happens is that a new dimension of as G
gets large a new dimension of space
materializes now that's crazy that's the
silliest thing I ever heard a new
dimension of space
materializes how can a dimension of
space materialize Well it can't but what
can happen is a very small compact
Direction can start to
expand I'm going to show you how it
works to some extent but let's just
begin with that let's take ordinary
space to start with to be
two-dimensional just for
pictures really we're talking about
10-dimensional String Theory let's take
ordinary space how many directions of
space does uh does 10-dimensional string
theory have no nine
the 10th Dimension is time right okay so
when when somebody tells you 10
dimensional String Theory they're
talking about a theory with nine
dimensions of
space okay so let's take a theory with
two dimensions of space just because I
can draw it on the Blackboard it's not
the right Theory but let's just draw it
on the Blackboard here's two dimensions
of
space now maybe
secretly that two-dimensional Space is
really three-dimensional how could it
really be
three-dimensional it could be
three-dimensional cuz
this CU there could be a thickness to
it we could imagine a
world sort of a peanut butter
sandwich uh with a piece of bread on
this side a piece of bread on this side
the bread being infinitely thin
and the peanut butter being real space
in
between but with a special rule the
Special Rule is that when an object goes
out here it reappears at the
bottom that's the idea of
compactification of periodicity that
there really isn't an edge to it but
when you go out one end when you go out
on the top piece of bread you reappear
on the bottom piece of bread then
there's no real Edge
somebody
moving vertically would not notice the
edge because when he got to the top
piece of bread he would just reappear at
the bottom piece of bread all right
that's uh that's the idea of an one
compact
Dimension now if the compact Dimension
was small
enough it might not be noticeable to the
physicists that live in this world that
the direction has a little that there's
this extra Dimension that this direction
has some that there's some thickness to
the world along a direction that they
didn't notice so they would call this
world
two-dimensional what happens as G starts
to
increase is that the peanut butter
sandwich gets thicker and thicker and
thicker and
eventually when G gets very large a
whole new dimension of space
materializes which the physicists who
lived in here would not be able to
ignore anymore they would have
discovered that they really live in a
world with an extra Dimension that is
what happens to this
Theory this theory that has dzero brains
and strings okay now you say
well what happens to the dzero brains
the thezero brains start getting lighter
and lighter just the same way that the
D1 brains did when G gets large they
start getting lighter and lighter and
lighter more and more simple but what do
they turn into they turn into the
gravitons in this extra dimensional
Theory just the ordinary
gravitons The Ordinary Elementary
particles that live in this extra
dimensional Theory this new theory is
now 11 dimensional we thought it was
string theory with only 10 dimensions
and when we started increasing this
coupling constant we discovered another
dimension of
space and these d0o brains just turned
into the gravitons that exist in
here another words again very very
complicated objects turn into very
simple light objects let me tell you
what happens to the strings to
understand the strings go back to the
thin sandwich
go back to the very thin
sandwich now remember I told you that
this theory has even dimensional
brains zero is even so it has d0o brains
but it also has D2 brains D4 brains D6
brains but concentrate in particular on
D2 brains what does a D2 brain mean
it means a
membrane it means a membrane you could
have two kinds of
membranes stuck into this
sandwich uh a membrane simply means a
surface a surface of energy you could
stick in a membrane in between the floor
and the ceiling in between the two
pieces of bread sort of embedded in the
peanut
butter right or if you lik you could
think of the top piece of bread is the
ceiling the bottom piece of bread is the
floor and then the two brains stuck in
between would be a floating Magic Carpet
that just uh that just hovered halfway
in between that's one kind of D brain to
D2 brain you could have there's another
kind that you can have and the other
kind is a kind of
ribbon let's see let's see if I can draw
it
it goes from the floor to the
ceiling but it's a ribbon sort of
stretched between the floor and the
ceiling
vertically which is extended in the
other
directions what happens when the floor
in the ceiling get closer and closer
what happens to this
ribbon it starts to look more and more
like a string it starts to look more and
more like a pointlike
string and so when G is very
small not a point-like string but a line
like string the line like strings are
just these membranes which are oriented
vertically in this direction
here as
and there are also the zero
brains the zero brains being very heavy
now you start to increase the coupling
constant the floor and the ceiling start
to
separate the the zero brains just turn
into gravitons they turn into just
gravitons moving in the extra
Dimension and they're very simple
they're just simple Elementary particles
in the higher dimensional
Theory what about the membranes or what
about the strings the strings now become
very very unstring
likee very very unstring
likee they have a lot of membrane in
them they're stretched a long ways
they're very heavy why are they he so
heavy because there's so
much material there vertically here they
turn into something very heavy the de
brains turned into something very light
this is an extremely bizarre story it is
one which
is the mathematics was discovered by a
bunch of
people uh and the consistency of it the
requirement for the need of
it was
um there was a lot of heavy mathematics
which went into
it the need for it to be consistent
involved conjectures mathematical
conjectures which the physicist didn't
know how to prove they were conjectures
about mathematical structures which
mathematicians knew about the
mathematicians had no idea about these
conjectures they' never heard of these
conjectures but when the physicist told
them look for these ideas to make any
sense such and such a mathematical
theorem has to be true the
mathematicians went back and said oh
yeah those MA those theorems turned out
to be true so there there's really very
little doubt that all of this holds
together as bizarre as it
sounds but it's just a whole collection
of examples of the breakdown of what I
called reductionism in the
beginning now the other
ingredient that makes it especially
bizarre is that all these things like
coupling constants can vary in space so
you can have a variation from place to
place where in some places the world
look very very close to 10 dimensional
with very light strings heavy d0o brains
and if you move over a couple of uh
meters or whatever the theory will
change its character develop a large
Direction in this direction strings will
turn into very heavy membranes and the
zero brains will turn into
gravitons these things are called
dualities these relationships between
what happens at one end of a parameter
space and the other end of a parameter
space and in in many ways they're very
magical and surprising
then nothing
like or was originally expected from
this Theory originally expected Was A
Simple Theory strings make up particles
end of
story
uh what turned out was much much more
complex and much more elusive in a
certain sense elusive in the sense that
it
just became totally unclear
what the starting objects of the theory
are what the starting objects what the
things which what the what the bricks
are and what the houses are and to this
day we really still simply don't know
what the what if anything the
fundamental objects that the theory is
built out of are if there are such
objects perhaps it's just this way
perhaps there is no set of objects which
are more fundamental than uh than the
strings and the brains and so forth and
they just transform into each other
perhaps there's something underlying the
whole
thing uh that's more fundamental than
any of them and can rearrange itself can
rearrange itself into different these
different patterns and form different
kinds of
structures so we don't know we don't
know the answer to those
questions all right let's take a break
for uh for 10
minutes let me just tell you a few more
interesting connections I was talking
about a few minutes ago with Michael and
a couple of other
people
um there's an enormous web of
interconnected ideas and interconnected
theories that string theory brings
together so let me show you uh two more
interesting ideas that
uh take a D3 brain remember now there
are those theories that have odd brains
and those theories that have even brains
let's take the case of the odd brain
theories which have D1 brains
fundamental strings and also D3 brains
now a D3 brain is like ordinary space it
has three dimensions in which you can
move around in if you were stuck on this
brain and you couldn't get off it
perhaps because you were attracted to it
uh you might think you're living in a
world of three dimensions
just as if there was a two-dimensional
membrane and you were a little creature
that moved around on the on the membrane
you would think you live in two
dimensions and you might not uh you know
under certain circumstances you might
really describe your world as being
pretty similar to uh to a quantum theory
or to a theory in two Dimensions two
space dimensions same thing in on three
brains three brains in many ways just
behave as if they were just ordinary
space
now the three brain itself can have all
sorts of Wiggles on it all sorts of
motions and uh it also has well has
among other things here's here's a
picture of a three brain no I think I
shall draw it the other
way let's draw it this
way you say that's not a three brain
it's a two brain too bad I can't draw
I'm not good at drawing
three-dimensional uh
figures imagine that it's
three-dimensional not two-dimensional
okay we're going to need the other
dimension for additional Dimensions so I
don't want to use the full three
dimensionals yeah you know what I mean
okay so that's a D3 brain and it can do
things it can have Wiggles on it and so
forth it can also have strings attached
to it like
that here's two strings attached to the
D3 brain ordinary strings those two
strings can come along here they are one
is over here one is over here they can
come along they can join and
form a single
string okay so here here's the picture
they come along they join and they form
a single string and then they go back
out and they do something else they
scatter they scatter they interact they
do all the things that particles
do and so on this world of three
dimensions which is not really the full
SpaceTime but just a brain all sorts of
things go on which are in many ways
similar to the things which happen in uh
in ordinary Quantum field theory in
three
dimensions well let me give
you one interesting
thought supposing from outside the D3
brain a fundamental string comes and
ends on the D3 brain how about the
people who live on this D3 brain who are
made up out of the strings wiggling up
and down the string what do they call
this object over here they call it a
particle right looks like a particle to
them it's a little point over here
somebody over here sees a little
particle over here
somehow may have come in from other some
other direction he doesn't see the other
directions only sees the directions he
lives in and uh sees a particle over
here what kind of particle this is now a
fundamental
string what kind of particle an
electrically charged
particle well if we can have fundamental
strings and in a theory with odd brains
we also have D strings so here's a d
string and a d string can also
end on a three brain that's part of the
mathematical story of D
brains fundamental strings and D strings
can end on the three brain that's a d
string what does that D string look like
to somebody living in here it also looks
like a
particle it's kind of a fatter particle
why is it fatter because the D string is
is fatter than the fundamental string
unless the coupling constant is very
large of course if the coupling constant
is very large they might get
interchanged but I'm in a world now
where the coupling constants is small
the fundamental strings are skinny and
threadlike the D strings are fat and
ropeik and a d string ending on here
would look like a bigger heavier
particle
this one looks like an electric charge
can you guess what this one looks
like a magnetic
monopole
so The
Duality that connects the fundamental
strings with the D strings Is Nothing
But The Duality which connected the
electric charges with the magnetic
charges of orinary field
Theory that's a that's a kind of
spectacular uh connection
that something we already knew for a
long
time has a new interpretation in terms
of D strings and fundamental strings The
Duality between D strings and
fundamental
strings I'll give you one more example
one more example which also involves D
strings and F strings and
I want you to go back to this 11
dimensional theory that we had over here
it's 11 Dimensions the horizontal uh
axis is 10 is nine dimensions of space
one extra dimension of space plus time
right let's go back to this Theory over
here but I unfortunately I can't draw
enough Dimensions to to do this
satisfactorily in this picture over here
here only one dimension of space is
compact the sandwich has only uh one uh
Direction along which it's sandwich like
okay I want to imagine taking two
dimensions of
space and compactifying them how can I
draw that well the maximum number of
Dimensions I can draw on the Blackboard
is three I can't draw more than three D
like the three dimensions on the
Blackboard if I compactify two two of
them that only gives me one more left to
to think of as all the other
dimensions so I'm just going to have to
make do with a world which has only one
large Dimension or at least one visible
large Dimension and two small ones what
does that look like it looks like this
here's the two small dimensions and
here's the one big Dimension which is a
standin for how many uh
seven
right okay now
imagine this is the same theory that had
D2
brains oh let's uh just for fun let's
draw
this as rather
asymmetric I'm going to draw it
asymmetrically so that
one of the axes is shorter than the
other to make a
point now this Theory also
has D2 brains the D2 brains were these
Str were these things which formed
strings when the sandwich was
small those strings sort of stretched
from the ceiling to the
floor here's the ceiling here's the
floor and we can draw those Str I wish
let me take another
color this happens to be a string which
is stretched out along the one visible
direction that I can draw here if I
could draw more directions I could make
the string wiggle and wave and so forth
uh but uh let's just stretch it out
along this direction it's a
string well it's not quite a string it's
sort of a
ribbon but if these directions are very
small then it looks like a string
right looks like a
string and what happens as the sandwich
in this Direction gets thinner and
thinner it gets more and more string
like of course but in fact it also gets
lighter and lighter because there's less
material
in the vertical Direction
here but we can also
put a string in and the other oriented
the other way
how about this string that's also from
the point of view of the large
dimensions of space it also looks like a
one-dimensional object as long as this
as long as both axes are
small what is this one called it's not
the same thing in fact which one of
these two strings would you think is
heavier the bottom War because there's
more material that way right
this one's heavy this one's light
they're both strings can you guess what
they
are F strings and D
strings so and this is another way to
think about uh to think about the
relation between F strings and D strings
their membranes which are wrapped around
two different directions two different
small directions
one of the directions being larger than
the
other now what happens if we imagine
taking the space and distorting it so
that we start squeezing this direction
this way and stretching this one that
way what happens to the two kinds of
strings the F strings get heavier and
heavier thicker and thicker more and
more material the D strings get lighter
and lighter
so we see again this is another way to
think about D strings and F strings
they're all mathematically
equivalent and it's just a small part of
an enormous network of
ideas uh that emerged out of string
theory connecting sometimes connecting
One String Theory with another String
Theory sometimes uh connecting String
Theory with Quantum field Theory
connecting ideas like mon poles and
charges with strings and other things
and
um most of it having very little to do
with what we see in the
laboratory
uh with that picture can't you view
Alpha as the ratio of the what's it can
we what in that picture can you view
Alpha as the ratio of the yes two
Dimensions yes that's EX exactly what it
is that's exactly what it is when the
ratio when this direction is small we
would normally call it uh a small
coupling constant and uh yeah yes that's
right and these things do not have uh a
a finite width because of cycal nature
well they have they they're finite and
extent but they're
cyclic right so so the bottom here is
the same point as the top so if you
walked along the ribbon and you came to
here you would reappear over
here likewise over here if you went out
over here you'd reappear over
here that gives you a kind of
infinity well you can go it's the same
kind of infinity as the Earth
okay it it's the same kind of infinity
as this circle you can go around it and
around around it but never come to the
end but nevertheless you wouldn't say
the distance around here was infinite no
but in this case you start out you go
this
direction uh you go up like this like a
step and then you then you appear to the
bottom and you go up another step in
other words if you add up if you add up
all the steps no what he was saying all
that is is going
around and around and around and around
it's just look it's taking a circle the
idea of going out the top and
reappearing at the bottom is nothing but
taking a circle where you just go around
and in order to mathematically exhibit
it you cut it open it
up draw it on the Blackboard is a line
but remember that this point and this
point are really the same point so that
when you go from here across you jump
across to here when you go out here you
come here why isn't this a helix right
than just a
circle at each point this is a circle
yes we're going along in this way and
therefore we get kind of a
helix well if you go around as you go
forward then you get a helix okay yeah
yes is there any this is of course
geometrical picture is there any uh
useful story about how the geometry here
connects to the uh earlier Point made
that the D brains can look like a
collection of f brains or you look very
closely and Scatter the D brain you see
a lot of f from this from this from this
picture that's a little bit hard to see
um it is useful it is useful but you
need a little bit more geometric
imagination to see how uh how a dbrain
can be connected up with an F brain and
um I'm reaching a saturation point of
complexity where where I
uh uh
where if you put the two in the same
picture mhm and then you
oscillated between the thin and the
narrow then you get them flip-flopping
perpendicular you mean oscillating in
space as you move along well I say if
you oscillate the long Dimension and the
short Dimension oscillate with time or
space or with what well either just the
shape I know but when you say oscillates
oscillates with respect just space
number space you just you're just going
to squish one this way and the other one
pops up exactly right exactly and if you
do them both in the same diagram then
you've got changing places that's right
exactly you could imagine that as you
move along space in this
direction it squishes horizontally and
broadens vert Al right so then you would
say over here the fundamental strings
are light over here the fundamental
strings are heavy now fundamental is
just a name all right it's quite clear
that which is fundamental and which
there's no there's no um preference for
which one is fundamental it's just a
word we call the ones which are arranged
vertically here fundamental we call the
ones which are arranged horizontal
D and that's right as you as you move
along here you can imagine going back
and forth or with time you could also
Imagine That with
time these uh and that can also happen
and so you could go back and forth
between the two of them
absolutely yeah uh now let me just uh
sort of finish
up the these thoughts by saying these
precise features are features
of um an
idealization the idealization is the
idealized super symmetric String Theory
super symmetric means that it has bons
and Fons of exactly the same mass
and it's an idealization in the sense
that it's not really
nature in some sense it's like the
idealization of studying perfectly
circular orbits why do you study
circular orbits because they're easy to
study
undoubtedly the first kind of orbit that
Newton studied circular orbits they had
an extra symmetry they were highly
symmetric and easy to study the
mathematics was easy right they weren't
the real planetary orbits but of course
many of the features of real planetary
orbits uh in simplified
form were there for circular
orbits again the kinds of string
theories that we really know how to deal
with mathematically string theory is
infinitely more uh complex than the
theory of
orbits the kind of theories that we know
how to deal with are also especially
symmetric symmetric meaning to say that
they have some mathematical properties
which are
idealizations makes them easy to
understand easier to understand and
uh uh but is not real
nature what they show us is the kind of
things that can
happen the kind of things all of these
things which happen here are expected to
have a reflection of one kind or another
in a more realistic Theory but it will
be more complicated and it will be uh
less tractable
and not so easy to visualize and
certainly not so easy to prove anything
about but it does show us the kind of
things that uh that can happen in a
string theory and very likely the kinds
of things that can happen more generally
than just just String
Theory so as I say String Theory as we
understand it now the piece that the
things that we really understand
mathematically are over
idealizations and so when
people argue in the press and then books
and uh silly books for the most part
about whether string theory is the Right
theory of the world or
not the answer is it's not it's just not
on the other hand does it have an
enormous amount to teach us about the
way that quantum mechanics gravity micro
structure fits together probably yes
that's my opinion in any
case um many of the things really don't
depend on the details of string
theory but uh okay enough of that
sermon um
there are other objects besides de
brains I don't I think I've probably
saturated you with ideas for tonight
there are other objects in the
theory there are things called fluxes
there are things called orbifolds things
called Orienta folds things all kinds of
structures uh which add to
the elements that you can put together
to create a
world you
can take a geometry for
example this room with the floor and the
ceiling being thought of as the top and
bottom of the peanut butter sandwich
maybe even uh periodically identified we
take that
wall uh we can take that uh this room
think of it really as one compact
Direction and two non-compact directions
and then we can put a d D2 brain into it
a Deb brain into it that fills up like a
flying carpet halfway between the floor
and the ceiling and that's a new
structure that could be there in space
you we shrink the size for the wall the
the floor to the ceiling but with that
flying carpet always stuck in between it
changes the character of physics in that
two-dimensional
world we can put one flying carpet in we
can put two flying carpets in we can put
three flying carpets in and we can make
a whole variety of different worlds by
changing the Deb brain content that we
put into the world as I said there are
other objects there are fluxes we can
change the nature of the microscopic
World by adding those things or
subtracting those
things what's String Theory gives us is
a bunch of tinkertoy parts a lot of
tinkertoy parts that we can play with
arrange rearrange do complicated things
with and in the process change what the
microscopic physics is like change what
particle physics is like change what uh
what the parameters of nature are
like it gives rise to huge numbers of
possibilities
permutations and combinations of how you
put these Tinker toy pieces
together how many
possibilities huge
number 10 to the 500 is a number that's
often thrown around incidentally it's
not very hard to get to 10 to the
um
supposing
yeah really all you need is 500 you
don't really need 500 is is not such big
number right supposing you have a
space which has which is like a dut
except it has 500 holes and Handles in
it now 500 holes and handles is not a
large number for the kind of spaces that
uh that string theory uses Cabo spaces
they're six-dimensional spaces they're
complicated 500 holes and handles
attached to them is not very
complicated now we can around each one
of what are called Cycles we can wrap
brains we can wrap fluxes if around each
one of 500 Cycles we can wrap a few
brains say three or four brains more or
less or we can put in a few fluxes or
whatever a flux is and modify the
geometry for each handle if we could
modif ify the structure in 10 different
ways then we would have 10 to the 500
possibilities you know it's kind of like
DNA you take a DNA
chain if the DNA chain was 500 units
long how many different creatures how
many different possibilities are there
for a
creature four to the 500 not 500 but
four to the 500 right so with the per
ation and
combinations of 500 objects being reach
being rearranged in maybe four five 10
ways you can make huge numbers of
possibilities and that's what happens
that's how many Tinker toy are given a
tinker toy set how many different uh
constructions can you make well you have
how many how many of those little wheels
and in each wheel you can uh put the you
know the numbers get very very large
so the same is true with string
theory
and the numbers are large and any given
construction is likely to be rather
complicated the generic construction
that you make is likely to be rather
complicated just like the generic
construction you can make with a DNA
chain uh well DNA chains are more than
500 units
long what 100 million units long 100
million base pairs long still only about
20,000 uh uh
genes how many kinds of creatures can
you make a huge number are any of them
simple well some of them are simple but
the generic uh creature that you make is
very complicated has Trunks and ears and
all sorts of uh all sorts of
appendages it could very well be that
that's the reason that particle physics
is so complicated
because a lot of moving Parts go into
constructing particular string theory
construction that's I think most string
theorists believe this by now that the
world is complicated because there's a
lot of moving Parts but not because the
rules are complicated the rules of DNA
are not complicated you have a long
chain and you either you put in a t a g
an A A C whatever whatever the uh base
pairs are and you put them in in
arbitrary uh sequence of uh of base
pairs and then what's that only four of
four of them what did I say TGC and a
yeah right right they come in pairs
though you realize on the other hand it
is yeah yeah but there's two uh there's
two strand there's two uh strands so if
you focus on one strand and you move
along it any point along it could be 10
four set so it's four to the 500 or
whatever four to the 30,000 whatever
um and none of them are particular
particularly simple but the rules the
basic underlying rules for putting
things together are simple the same is
true of string here and very much very
much the same way that the basic rules
for what you're allowed to do are pretty
simple the number of Arrangements that
you can make for a particular setup is
very large and most of them will lead
the Fairly complicated uh particle
physics that's the situation we're
facing and um the string theory if
string theory is correct I think we
should expect that uh
that um that particle physics will be
more complicated probably than we'll
ever able be able to unravel
completely question is it thought that
the of the four to uh 10 to 500 that
that there really only a few that
describ this 10th of the 500
incidentally is an underestimate that
was a yeah but go ahead but is thought
that that if we had all the information
that we would find out only one or a
couple of anal I I know about The
Duality that you've talked yeah yeah
there are the dualities but uh when you
sort of when you when you divide out the
dualities the 10 to the 500 is the
number that's left over and it's not 10
to the 500 that's an old
number but I mean is it only a few that
would would if we knew what it was it
would only be one of those choices
presumably so presumably
so but there may be many which look very
similar there may be many many which
look very very similar you know there
may be a lot of junk DNA in it and
uh but are there some where like for
example in this picture that the aspect
ratio were one and therefore the F and
the D's were kind of the same thing
right like are there some are those 10
to the 500 where the whole thing becomes
a lot simpler there are I think you're
asking whether there are specially
symmetric points and there are specially
symmetric points yeah uh there are
specially symmetric points our world
does not seem to be one of those
specially symmetric
points um a specially symmetric point
would be one in which the monopole mass
and the electron Mass were the
same apparently we don't live in that
world we live in a lopsided World more
like this
do we know why
no I long long ago I studied
Communications engineering here at
Stanford and the at that time what they
taught us about coding Theory and
communication error correction codes was
that and this is always said with a
sense of dire humor that almost all the
codes you can find are really very very
good but because the only ones you can
decode have mathematical structure the
ones you can actually decode are
universally bad bad in what sense in bad
they don't give you the they give just a
fraction of the performance that you
could get to now it's turned out uh that
uh in the many years since I studied
this that they have in fact found codes
that are unbelievably good compared to
what we had back in the 70s but it
reminds me of this that that it's the
mathematical
structure when that if the mathematical
structure is is understandable the
complexity is too low to explain yeah
almost anything you can name is too
simple to be
interesting like almost every number is
small because any number you name almost
all of them are much
bigger H anything you can describe is
probably to uh you know describe in a
small number of uh of
bits yeah this is probably true and um I
think what it means if true if these
things are true is we've got to learn to
ask a new class of questions the
question is not exactly what is the
setup which uh what are the common
features what are the generic features
what the and um you know with people are
wrestling with those questions
biolog yeah yeah yeah now will it turn
out that way we don't know this this is
this is uh but uh it doesn't do anybody
any good to have
um ideological Warfare in the Press over
these
things
okay yes sir uh it seems that there
wouldn't be a big difference
between you Leonard no no he's
Leonard right hi
leard it seems that there wouldn't be a
big difference between a uh um compact
direction that has a very large size and
an
infinite well and and so do we know that
we that our three ordinary Dimensions
really are infinite nope we do
not we do not we do
not as a matter of fact I mean you know
standard uh oldfashioned cosmological
theor said the three dimensions form a
sphere a growing sphere to be sure
but a three spere and so they were all
compact all compact but growing so no we
don't and and there's no way to actually
tell we can only say that they're bigger
than this or
that the the measured flatness of the
universe you know if you want to know
how big the Earth was
around you going out in the farmers fi
field which is uh you know a uh a
kilometer by a kilometer and looking
around all he could do is put a bound on
how big the Earth is from looking at
triangles and things and over small
distances you can say well the Earth is
so flat that I suspect it must be at
least 60 Mi
big does a little bit better measures a
little more accurately triangles at the
surface of the Earth assuming the
surface of the Earth was nice and flat
anded didn't have Hills in it he might
be able to say it's 500 mil big or
bigger and that's all it can do until he
starts to detect the curvature of the
earth and when he detects the curvature
of the earth then he say aha the earth
looks like it's 24,000 miles in
circumference same thing when we look
out
cosmologically space looks very flat on
very large scales so all we can say is
it's at least this big
it's at
least
um 40 billion light years on a side well
it's bigger than that no no it's much
bigger than that 400 light years on a
side at least at
minimum and
um but we can't we can't say uh one way
or another whether it's infinite or
not yeah if G can vary over space how
would you be able to detect whether your
in the real world it can't in the real
world which is not as symmetric and as
simple as this it it can't but
no no
it it may be able to vary but it'll vary
in
steps it'll V we're going to talk about
this when we talk about cosmology what
are the kinds of uh what are the kinds
of
variations that the laws of physics can
have from place to place consistent with
both Theory and with what we know
experimentally and from what we know
experimentally is that these changes
take have to take place in discrete
jumps more or less in jumps okay because
if it was continuous it would seem that
you can move along a linear Dimension
and then end up in one of the curved
dimensions that's become big and and
perhaps yeah know I I think we know with
pretty much certainty that it can't
continuously smoothly vary what we don't
know is whether it can vary in jumps and
there are good reasons to think that it
varies in jumps so what happens to a
compact qu dimension in a high
gravitational field say close to a black
hole it get squished down uh some kinds
of black holes
yes other kinds no ordinary schi black
hole no it doesn't get not not in the
Horizon of a Schwarz shill black hole
no Horizon of a Schwarz Shi black hole
is a very ordinary place where nothing
special like that happens I'm losing my
voice
uh for more please visit us at
stanford.edu